<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!-- This file is part of the book                      -->
<!--                                                    -->
<!--   Contemporary Pre-Calculus Through Applications   -->
<!--                                                    -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2017  Mathematics Department, NCSSM  -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.       -->
<section xml:id="chapter04-section03" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Geometric Growth and Decay</title>
  <p>Some recursively defined functions have important applications in life.  One of the simplest, yet most important, represents <em>geometric decay</em>. In geometric decay, the value of the function at time <m>n</m> is directly proportional to the value at time. This relationship suggests a recursive definition for geometric decay. The first example from Section <xref ref="chapter04-section01" text="local"/>, Example <xref ref="ibuprofen-example-one-dose" text="local"/>, involved the amount of ibuprofen in Joan's system at time <m>n</m> if she takes a single <m>200</m> mg tablet. Since her body filters out <m>67\%</m> of the ibuprofen present, the amount remaining after <m>n</m> time intervals is always <m>33\%</m> of the amount remaining after <m>n-1</m> time intervals.</p>
  <p>In that case, we calculated the amount of drug in Joan's boady with the recursive system</p>
  <md>
    <mrow>D_0=200, D_n=0.33 \cdot D_{n-1}, n=1,2,3,...</mrow>
  </md>
  <example xml:id="example-fading-blue-jeans">
    <title>Fading Blue Jeans</title>
    <statement>
      <p>Blue jeans fade when they are washed. Suppose a pair of jeans loses <m>2\%</m> of its color with each washing.  How much of the original color is left after <m>50</m> washes?</p>
    </statement>
    <solution>
      <statement>
        <p>In this problem, we use the system</p>
        <md>
          <mrow>C_0=1, C_n=0.98 \cdot C_{n-1}, n=1,2,3,...</mrow>
        </md>
        <p>where <m>C_n</m> is the amount of color remaining in the jeans after <m>n</m> washings</p>
        <p>We use <m>1</m> as the initial value to represent all or <m>100\%</m> of the color.  Since we want to measure the amount of color remaining, the coefficient in the recursive equation is <m>0.98</m>.  With <m>50</m> iterations of the equation for <m>C_n</m>, we find that the jeans have about <m>36\%</m> of their original color left after <m>50</m> washings.</p>
      </statement>
    </solution>
  </example>

  <example xml:id="example-electrical-power-demand">
    <title>Electrical Power Demand</title>
    <statement>
      <p>The amount of electrical power used by a community is increasing by 5% per year.  This year, they used 500 thousand kilowatt-hours of electrical power.  How many years will it take until the electrical power consumption for this community has doubled?</p>
    </statement>
    <solution>
      <statement>
        <p>This is an example of <em>geometric growth</em>, since the amount of power is increasing each year. We use the recursive system</p>
        <md>
          <mrow>P_0=500, P_n=1.05 \cdot P_{n-1}, n=1,2,3,...</mrow>
        </md>
        <p>Since the amount of power used is increasing by <m>5\%</m> each year, next year the citizens of the community will use <m>105\%</m> of what they used this year.  By iterating the equation for <m>P_n</m>, we find that after <m>14</m> years the community will use about <m>990</m> thousand kwh per year and after <m>15</m> years they will use about <m>1039</m> thousand kwh per year.  The amount of power required by the community will have doubled in a little less than <m>15</m> years.  Note that this conclusion assumes that the demand for electrical power continues to increase by <m>5\%</m> per year.</p>
      </statement>
    </solution>
  </example>

  <example xml:id="example-radioactive-decay">
    <title>Radioactive Decay</title>
    <statement>
      <p>Potassium-42 is a radioactive element that is often used in biological experiments as a tracer element.  Potassium-42, like all radioactive elements, decays into a non-radioactive form at a rate proportional to the amount present.  Potassium-42 loses <m>5.545\%</m> of its mass every hour.  If <m>1</m> milligram of potassium-42 is initially present in an animal, at what time will only <m>0.1</m> milligram be present?</p>
    </statement>
    <solution>
      <statement>
        <p>Note that the effect of losing <m>5.545\%</m> is equivalent to retaining <m>94.455\%</m>. We use the recursive system</p>
        <md>
          <mrow>P_0=1, P_n=0.94455 \cdot P_{n-1}, n=1,2,3,...</mrow>
        </md>
        <p>We are interested in finding the amount of time until <m>P_n</m> is less than or equal to <m>0.1</m>.  Iterating the equation for <m>P_n</m>, we find that <m>P_{40} = 0.1021</m> and <m>P_{41} = 0.0964</m>. So after <m>40</m> hours, <m>0.1021</m> mg of potassium-42 remain, and after <m>41</m> hours, <m>0.0964</m> mg remain. Sometime between <m>40</m> and <m>41</m> hours we expect to have only <m>0.1</m> mg of potassium-42 remaining.</p>

        <p>The recursive system we used to generate amounts of potasium-42 does not allow us to determine the amount present between the <m>40^{th}</m> hour and the <m>41^{st}</m> hour.  The amount of potassium-42 changes incrementally between the <m>40^{th}</m> and the <m>41^{st}</m> hours, but the recursive equation we have used to represent this phenomenon cannot give us information about potassium levels between <m>P_{40}</m> and <m>P_{41}</m>.</p>
      </statement>
    </solution>
  </example>

  <p>Each of the three previous examples uses a recursive system that can be written as </p>
  <md>
    <mrow>Y_0=a,Y_n=(1+k) \cdot Y_{n-1}, n=1,2,3, ...</mrow>
  </md>
  <p> If <m>k \gt 0</m>, this system represents geometric growth (with growth rate <m>k</m>); as <m>n</m> increases, the value of <m>Y_n</m>  increases.  If <m>k \lt 0</m>, the system represents geometric decay (and <m>k</m> is the decay rate); as <m>n</m> increases, the value of <m>Y_n</m>  decreases.  In either case, the next value of <m>Y_n</m> depends entirely on the value of <m>k</m> and the old value of <m>Y_n</m>.</p>
  <p>Geometric growth that can be described with a recursive system can also be described by an explicit function.  To demonstrate, we will iterate the system used in Example <xref ref="example-radioactive-decay" text="local" /> to describe electricity consumption</p>
  <md>
    <mrow>P_0=500</mrow>
    <mrow>P_1=(1+0.05)P_0</mrow>
    <mrow>P_2=(1+0.05)P_1</mrow>
    <mrow>P_3=(1+0.05)P_2</mrow>
    <mrow>P_4=(1+0.05)P_3</mrow>
  </md>
  <p>We can rewrite each of these equations in terms of <m>P_0</m>, which yields</p>
  <md>
    <mrow>P_1=(1.05)P_0</mrow>
    <mrow>P_2=(1.05) P_1=(1.05) (1.05)P_0=(1.05)^2 P_0</mrow>
    <mrow>P_3=(1.05) P_2=(1.05) (1.05)^2 P_0=(1.05)^3 P_0</mrow>
    <mrow>P_4=(1.05) P_3=(1.05) (1.05)^3 P_0=(1.05)^4 P_0</mrow>
  </md>
  <p>If we continue this process, we see that the <m>n^{th}</m> term is given by</p>
  <md>
    <mrow>P_n=(1.05)^n P_0</mrow>
  </md>
  <p>In general, we can convert the recursive system for geometric growth or decay, namely</p>
  <md>
    <mrow>Y_0=a,Y_n=(1+k) \cdot Y_{n-1}, n=1,2,3, ...</mrow>
  </md>
  <p>to an explicit function in terms of <m>a, k, </m>and <m>n</m>, as follows:</p>
  <md>
    <mrow>Y_0=a</mrow>
    <mrow>Y_1=(1+k)Y_0 = (1+k)a</mrow>
    <mrow>Y_2=(1+k)Y_1 = (1+k)(1+k)a = a(1+k)^2</mrow>
    <mrow>Y_3=(1+k)Y_2 = (1+k)a(1+k)^2 = a(1+k)^3</mrow>
  </md>
  <p>If we continue this process, we see that the <m>n^{th}</m> term is given by</p>
  <md>
    <mrow>Y_n=a(a+k)^n</mrow>
  </md>
  <p>Note the distinction between the recursive equation</p>
  <md>
    <mrow>Y_n=Y_{n-1}(1+k)</mrow>
  </md>
  <p>and the explicit equation</p>
  <md>
    <mrow>Y_n=a(1+k)^n</mrow>
  </md>
  <p>The recursive equation shows that each value of <m>Y_n</m>  is obtained from the preceding value by multiplying by <m>(1+k)</m>. The explicit equation uses an exponent to represent this repeated multiplication.</p>
  <p>If we wanted the value of <m>Y_{100}</m>, the recursive equation would require that values of <m>Y_1, Y_2, Y_3,</m> and so forth up to <m>Y_{99}</m>,  all be calculated. In contract, the explicit equaiotn <m>Y_n=a(1+k)^n</m> allows us to calculate <m>Y_{100}</m> without requiring any intermediate values.</p>
  <p>The explicit equation can be rewritten using the more traditional functional notation:</p>
  <definition xml:id="explicit-geometric-growth-equation">
    <title>Explicit Function for Geometric Growth</title>
    <statement>
      <md>
        <mrow>Y(n)=a(1+k)^n</mrow>
      </md>
    </statement>
  </definition>
  <p>In equation <xref ref="explicit-geometric-growth-equation" text="local" /> the independent variable <m>n</m> is in the exponent, so this function is an exponential function. The exponential function <m>Y(n)=a(1+k)^n</m> is the closed form representation of the recursive system  <m>Y_0=a,Y_n=(1+k)Y_{n-1}</m></p>

  <example xml:id="example-one-time-bank-desposit">
    <statement>
      <p>Suppose you plan to make a one-time deposit into a bank account that will earn <m>0.45\%</m> monthly interest.  How large must this deposit be so that you will have a college fund of <m>\$75,000</m> available after <m>18</m> years or <m>216</m> months?</p>
    </statement>
    <solution>
      <statement>
        <p>We can solve this problem using the recursive model <m>S_0 = a</m>, <m>S_n = (1.0045) S_{n-1}</m> but we will have to guess and check to find the appropriate value of <m>S_0</m> that gives of <m>S_{216} = 75,000</m>.  Using the closed form <m>S(n)=a(1.0045)^n</m> , we need to find the value of <m>a</m> such that <m>75,000 = a (1.0045)^{216}</m>.  Solving for <m>a</m> gives the equation <m>a = \frac{75,000}{(1.0045)^{216}}</m> , or <m>a = \$28,436.36</m>.  We see that the closed form is useful when we do not need all the intermediate values that the recursive form generates.</p>
      </statement>
    </solution>
  </example>

  <example xml:id="example-continuous-discrete">
    <title>Continuous Versus Discrete</title>
    <statement>
      <p>In Example <xref ref="example-radioactive-decay" text="local" /> we considered the amount of Potassium-42 that remains present during the decay process.  We used the recursive system</p>
      <md>
        <mrow>P_0=1, P_n=0.94455P_{n-1}, n=1,2,3,...</mrow>
      </md>
      <p>to determine the amount of Potassium-42 remaining after <m>n</m> 1-hour time intervals.</p>
      <p>We could also use the explicit function</p>
      <md>
        <mrow>P(t)=1 \cdot (0.944355)^t</mrow>
      </md>
      <p>to represent the amount of Potassium-42 remaining <m>t</m> hours after the decay process begins. Use each of these representations to determine how much Potassium remains after <m>12</m> hours.</p>
    </statement>
    <solution>
      <statement>
        <p>This is what our work looks like if we use the recursive system:</p>
        <md>
          <mrow>P_0=1</mrow>
          <mrow>P_1=0.94455 \cdot P_0 = 0.94455</mrow>
          <mrow>P_2=0.94455 \cdot P_1 = 0.94455 \cdot 0.94455 = 0.892175</mrow>
          <mrow>P_3=0.94455 \cdot P_2 = 0.94455 \cdot 0.892175 = 0.847036</mrow>
          <mrow>P_4=0.94455 \cdot P_3 = 0.94455 \cdot 0.847036 = 0.7959757</mrow>
          <mrow>...</mrow>
          <mrow>P_{12}=0.94455 \cdot P_{11} = 0.94455 \cdot 0.53392 = 0.5043121</mrow>
        </md>
        <p>If we use the explicit function:</p>
        <md>
          <mrow>P(12)=1(0.94455)^{12} = 0.5043121</mrow>
        </md>
        <p>Both representations tell us that in <m>12</m> hours the amount of Potassium-42 will have decreased from <m>1</m> milligram to about <m>0.5</m> milligram.</p>
        <p>We need to be aware of the advantages and disadvantages of each representation that we used in Example <xref ref="example-one-time-bank-desposit" text="local" />. The recursive system is inherently discrete.  Values of <m>P_n</m> can be calculated only for positive interger values of <m>n</m>, where n counts the number of <m>1</m>-hour time intervals that have elapsed since we measured <m>1</m> milligram of potassium-42. The recursive representation is not able to tell us anything about the amount of potassium present between <m>P_2</m> and <m>P_3</m>, in fact, <m>P_{2.7}</m> is not even defined.</p>
        <p>The explicit function <m>P(t)=1 \cdot (0.944355)^t</m> uses <m>t</m> as a variable whose domain is all positive real numbers and <m>P(2.7)</m> is well-defined and meaningful. The explicit function can tell us the amount of Potassium-42 present at any time on the continuum between zero and infinity.</p>
        <p>Graphs of both the recursive and the explicit representations are shown below</p>

        <sidebyside widths ="50% 50%">
          <figure xml:id="figure-discrete-p42">
            <caption>Mg of Potassium Over Time: Discrete and Continuous Models</caption>
            <image xml:id="plot-discrete-p42">
              <latex-image-code>
                <![CDATA[
                \begin{tikzpicture}
                \begin{axis}[
                axis line style = {<->},
                width = 0.5\linewidth,
                xlabel = 1-hour time periods,
                y label style={at={(axis description cs:0,.5)}},
                ylabel = Mg of Potassium,
                label style={font=\tiny},
                xmin = -2, xmax = 17,
                ymin = -0.2, ymax = 1.2,
                ytick = {0,0.1, ...,1.2},
                xtick = {0, 1, ...,17},
                tick label style={font=\tiny},
                ]

                \addplot table [only marks, x index = {0}, y index = {1}, col sep=comma]{data-potassium-42.csv};

                \end{axis}
                \end{tikzpicture}]]>
              </latex-image-code>
            </image>
          </figure>

          <figure xml:id="figure-continuous-p42">
            <caption>Mg of Potassium Over Time: Discrete and Continuous Models</caption>
            <image xml:id="plot-continuous-p42">
              <latex-image-code>
                <!-- CDATA prevents certain LaTeX code from being interpreted as xml -->
                <![CDATA[
                \begin{tikzpicture}
                \begin{axis}[
                axis line style = {<->},
                width = 0.5\linewidth,
                xlabel = Elapsed Time (hrs),
                y label style={at={(axis description cs:0,.5)}},
                ylabel = Mg of Potassium,
                label style={font=\tiny},
                xmin = -2, xmax = 17,
                ymin = -0.2, ymax = 1.2,
                ytick = {0,0.1, ...,1.2},
                xtick = {0, 1, ...,17},
                tick label style={font=\tiny},
                ]

                \addplot [thick, blue, <->, mark=none, domain=-1:17]{0.944355^x};

                \end{axis}
                \end{tikzpicture}]]>
              </latex-image-code>
            </image>
          </figure>
        </sidebyside>
        <p>Note that in the graph on the left, the horizontal scale shows the number of <m>1</m>-hour time intervals that have elapsed since <m>P_0</m>. On the right, the horizontal scale shows elapsed time. This is consistent with the fact that the recursive system has domain <m>n=1,2,3,...</m> and the explicit function has domain all positive real numbers.</p>
      </statement>
    </solution>
  </example>

  <p>Example <xref ref="example-continuous-discrete" text="type-local" /> shows that we must pay attention to issues of domain when we are choosing between using recursive and explicit representations of a particular phenomenon. Some phenomena by their very nature have a discrete (and thus discontinuous) domain, and these are often best represented recursively. Other phenomena are by nature continuous and may be better represented by an explicit function. Of course, with appropriate care about interpretations, we can choose to use a continuous function to represent a discrete phenomenon.  We can also use a discrete representation for a continuous phenomenon. If we choose to do this, we need to pay particular attention to the way that we interpret our calculations.</p>


  <exercises>
    <title>Class Practice</title>
    <exercise>
      <statement>
        <p>When a basketball is released and drops to a hard surface, it's path looks something like what is shown in the photo.</p>
        <figure>
          <caption></caption>
          <image source="src/images/bouncing_ball_strobe_edit.jpg" width = "50%" />
        </figure>
        <p>Each time that it bounces, it rebounds to <m>75\%</m> of the height from which it was released (assuming that the ball is correctly inflated.) If a ball is dropped from <m>3</m> meters, we can write the recursive system</p>
        <md>
          <mrow>H_0=3, H_n = 0.75 H_{n-1}</mrow>
        </md>
        <figure>
          <caption></caption>
          <image xml:id="plot-basketball-bounce">
            <latex-image-code>
              <![CDATA[
              \begin{tikzpicture}
              \begin{axis}[
              axis line style = {<->},
              width = 0.5\linewidth,
              xlabel = Number of Bounces,
              y label style={at={(axis description cs:0,.5)}},
              ylabel = Rebound Height (meters),
              label style={font=\tiny},
              xmin = -2, xmax = 8,
              ymin = -0.2, ymax = 3.25,
              ytick = {0, .25, ...,3},
              xtick = {0, 1, ...,7},
              tick label style={font=\tiny},
              ]

              \addplot[only marks, color=blue] coordinates {
              (0,  3)
              (1,  2.25)
              (2,  1.6875)
              (3,  1.265625)
              (4,  0.94921875)
              (5,  0.711914063)
              (6,  0.533935547)
              (7, 0.40045166)
              };

              \end{axis}
              \end{tikzpicture}]]>
            </latex-image-code>
          </image>
        </figure>
        <p>The graph  shows the rebound height on the vertical axis and bounce number on the horizontal. Sketch a graph of the associated explicit function  <m>h(t)=3(0.75)^t</m> where <m>h(t)</m> is the height at time <m>t</m>. Explain how the graph you sketch is related to the discrete graph that is shown.</p>
      </statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise>
      <statement>
        <p>In Example <xref ref="example-fading-blue-jeans" text="type-local"/> we used the recursive system <m>C_0=1, C_n = 0.98C_{n-1}</m> to represent the amount of color left in blue jeans after <m>n</m> washings. The graph shows remaining color on the vertical axis and number of washings on the horizontal axis. Sketch a graph of the associated explicit function <m>C(t)=1(0.98)^t</m> where <m>t</m> represents elapsed time.  Write a few sentences to explain how and why your graph differs from the discrete graph shown.</p>

        <figure>
          <caption></caption>
          <image xml:id="plot-jeans-class-practice">
            <latex-image-code>
              <![CDATA[
              \begin{tikzpicture}
              \begin{axis}[
              axis line style = {<->},
              width = 0.5\linewidth,
              xlabel = Number of Washes,
              y label style={at={(axis description cs:0,.5)}},
              ylabel = Percent Color Remaining,
              label style={font=\tiny},
              xmin = -2, xmax = 15,
              ymin = -0.2, ymax = 1.2,
              ytick = {0, .2, ...,1},
              xtick = {0, 1, ...,14},
              tick label style={font=\tiny},
              ]

              \addplot[only marks, color=blue] coordinates {
              (0,  1)
              (1,  0.98)
              (2,  0.9604)
              (3,  0.941192)
              (4,  0.92236816)
              (5,  0.903920797)
              (6,  0.885842381)
              (7,  0.868125533)
              (8,  0.850763023)
              (9,  0.833747762)
              (10,  0.817072807)
              (11,  0.800731351)
              (13,  0.769022389)
              (12,  0.784716724)
              (14,  0.753641941)
              };

              \end{axis}
              \end{tikzpicture}]]>
            </latex-image-code>
          </image>
        </figure>
      </statement>
    </exercise>
  </exercises>

  <example xml:id="example-recursive-salary">
    <statement>
      <p>Rebecca starts working for a company at a salary of <m>\$40,000</m> per year. Based on the company's history, she can expect raises of <m>3.5\%</m> each year on the anniversary of her employment. When will she first make <m>\$50,000</m>?</p>
    </statement>
    <solution>
      <statement>
        <p>We can use the recursive system <m>A_0=40,000, A_n=1.035A_{n-1}, n=1,2,3,...</m> to determine when her salary will equal or exceed <m>\$50,000</m>.  Rebecca’s first pay raise will result in a salary of <m>\$41,400</m>.  Her sixth raise will bring her salary up to <m>\$49,170.21</m> and her seventh raise will put her pay over <m>\$50,000</m> at <m>\$50,891.17</m>.</p>

        <p>We could also use a closed form function to solve for the time at which her salary will reach <m>\$50,000</m>.  This function is <m>S(t)=40,000(1.035)^t</m>. By evaluating this function, we find that <m>S(6)=49,170.21</m> and <m>S(7)=50,891.17</m>. Both the recursive model and the closed form model inform us that Rebecca will make more than <m>\$50,000</m> with her <m>7^{th}</m> raise.</p>

        <p>If we wanted to know what Rebecca would make if she stayed with this company for <m>30</m> years, it would be easier to use the closed form and substitute <m>t=30</m>.  In many cases either the recursive system or the closed form could be used to arrive at the same answer. In cases where we need to predict far into the future, it is more efficient to use the closed form. In cases where we want to see all of the intermediate values, as would be the case for the balance due on a loan after each payment, it would be to our advantage to use the recursive system. In Rebecca's case, if we choose to use an explicit representation we must limit the domain to integer values since her pay raises occur only one time per year.</p>
      </statement>
    </solution>
  </example>

  <example xml:id="example-doubling-time">
    <title>Doubling Time</title>
    <statement>
      <p>Suppose the population of a certain type of bacteria is known to grow geometrically and increases by about <m>26\%</m> every hour. How much time will it take for a population of <m>150</m> million cells to grow to <m>300</m> million? How long will it take the population to double again to <m>600</m> million? When will the population reach <m>1200</m> million (another doubling)?</p>
    </statement>
    <solution>
      <statement>
        <p>Since the population is growing by <m>26\%</m> per hour, we can use the recursive system</p>
        <md>
          <mrow>P_0 = 150, P_n = (1.26)P_{n-1}</mrow>
        </md>
        <p>We also have the option of using the explicit function <m>P(t)=150 \cdot (1.26)^t</m>.  For integer values of <m>t</m>, these two representations give roughly identical values for the number of bacteria cells.</p>
        <sidebyside widths ="50% 50%">
          <table>
            <caption></caption>
            <tabular bottom="medium">
              <row bottom="major">
                <cell right="medium">Time (Hours)</cell>
                <cell>Cells (Millions)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell right="medium"><m>0</m></cell>
                <cell><m>150</m></cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell right="medium"><m>1</m></cell>
                <cell><m>189</m></cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell right="medium"><m>2</m></cell>
                <cell><m>238.14</m></cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell right="medium"><m>3</m></cell>
                <cell><m>300.06</m></cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell right="medium"><m>4</m></cell>
                <cell><m>378.07</m></cell>
              </row>

            </tabular>
          </table>

          <table>
            <caption></caption>
            <tabular bottom="medium">
              <row bottom="major">
                <cell right="medium">Time (Hours)</cell>
                <cell>Cells (Millions)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell right="medium"><m>5</m></cell>
                <cell><m>476.37</m></cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell right="medium"><m>6</m></cell>
                <cell><m>600.22</m></cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell right="medium"><m>7</m></cell>
                <cell><m>756.28</m></cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell right="medium"><m>8</m></cell>
                <cell><m>952.92</m></cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell right="medium"><m>9</m></cell>
                <cell><m>1200.67</m></cell>
              </row>
            </tabular>
          </table>

        </sidebyside>

        <p>The population took about <m>3</m> hours to double from <m>150</m> to <m>300</m> million.  In another <m>3</m> hours, it had doubled again, and in another <m>3</m> hours there was yet another population doubling. This population is said to have a <em>doubling time</em> of <m>3</m> hours. Note that the first doubling corresponds to an increase of <m>150</m> cells, the next doubling is an increase of <m>300</m> cells, and the third doubling is an increase of <m>600</m> cells. For each of these doublings, the elapsed time is the same (<m>3</m> hours) but the increase, measured in cells per hour, is not the same.</p>
      </statement>
    </solution>
  </example>
  <p>Example <xref ref="example-doubling-time" text="local"/> shows that a population that experiences geometric growth has a doubling time. It is also true that populations that experience geometric decay have a <em>half-life</em>. A half-life is the amount of time it takes for a population size to be halved. Populations that experience other types of growth, such as linear, quadratic or logistic, do not have a doubling time.</p>

  <p>The exponential function you studied in Chapter 2, <m>f(t)=2^t</m>, has a doubling time of <m>1</m> time unit. This is because</p>
  <md>
    <mrow>f(1)=2^1=2</mrow>
    <mrow>f(2)=2^2=4</mrow>
    <mrow>f(3)=2^3=8</mrow>
    <mrow>f(4)=2^4=16</mrow>
  </md>
  <p>A doubling of function-values takes place with each increase of <m>1</m> unit in <m>t</m></p>
  <p>The function <m>g(t)=2^{\frac{1}{3} t}</m> is a horizontal stretch of the function <m>f(t)=2^t</m>, and this transformation makes <m>g(t)</m> have a doubling time of <m>3</m> time units:</p>
  <md>
    <mrow>g(3)=2^{\frac{1}{3} \cdot 3}=2^1=2</mrow>
    <mrow>g(6)=2^{\frac{1}{3} \cdot 6}=2^2=4</mrow>
    <mrow>g(9)=2^{\frac{1}{3} \cdot 9}=2^3=8</mrow>
  </md>
  <p>Since <m>g(t)=2^{\frac{1}{3} t}</m> has a doubling time of <m>3</m> time units, in Example <xref ref="example-doubling-time" text="local"/> we could have used the function <m>y = 150 \cdot 2^{\frac{1}{3} t}</m> to model the number of bacteria cells present at time <m>t</m>. You can confirm that the two functions <m>y = 150 \cdot 2^{\frac{1}{3} t}</m> and <m>P(t)=150 \cdot (1.26)^t</m> produce roughly the same ordered pairs.</p>

  <exercises>
    <exercisegroup>
      <introduction><p>In exercises <m>1</m> through <m>4</m>, identify whether the growth (or decay) that is described is discrete or continuous.  Write either a recursive system or an expliciit function to represent the phenomenon. Use the most appropriate form to answer each question.</p></introduction>
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>Research City is growing by <m>14\%</m> each year.  If the population of the city is approximately one million people and the rate of growth continues at <m>14\%</m> annually, what will Research City's population be <m>15</m> years from now?</p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>

      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>The population of Coastal City grows by <m>3\%</m> each year due only to births and deaths among current residents.  The population is currently one million.  Each year <m>15,000</m> more people move into the city than move out, resulting in a net gain of <m>0.015</m> milion people. How long will it take Coastal City's population to reach <m>1.8</m> million people?</p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>

      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>Each year hunting and natural predators combine to cause the population of rabbits in the meadow to decrease by <m>5\%</m>.  If the year begins with <m>230</m> rabbits and the population continues to decrease by <m>5\%</m> each year, how many rabbits will there be in this meaudow in <m>50</m> years?</p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>

      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>Each year the population of rabbits in the meadow decreases by <m>5\%</m>.  Farmer Dan decides to help the rabbit population by releasing <m>5</m> new rabbits into the meadow each year.  If the year begins with <m>230</m> rabbits, describe what will happen to the population over the next ten years.</p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>
    </exercisegroup>

    <exercise>
      <statement>
        <p>An annual inflation rate of <m>k\%</m> means that items will cost <m>k\%</m> more next year than they cost this year.  Based on a yearly inflation rate of <m>3\%</m>, estimate the cost of the following items in <m>10</m>, <m>20</m>, <m>30</m>, and <m>40</m> years.</p>

        <table>
          <caption></caption>
          <tabular bottom="medium">
            <row bottom="major">
              <cell right="medium">Item</cell>
              <cell>Cost Today</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell right="medium">Jeans</cell>
              <cell><m>\$45.00</m></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell right="medium">Hamburger</cell>
              <cell><m>\$3.90</m></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell right="medium">Car</cell>
              <cell><m>\$29,000</m></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell right="medium">Textbook</cell>
              <cell><m>\$75.00</m></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell right="medium">Movie Ticket</cell>
              <cell><m>\$9.00</m></cell>
            </row>

          </tabular>
        </table>
      </statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise>
      <statement>
        <p>How much money would you need to invest now in an account that receives <m>0.5\%</m> monthly interest so that in <m>20</m> years you will have <m>\$50,000</m>?</p>
      </statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise>
      <statement>
        <p>The number of cells in a certain bacteria colony triples every hour.  Write an explicit function that models this growth.  By what factor does the population grow in half an hour?</p>
      </statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise>
      <statement>
        <p>Thorieum-<m>234</m> is a radioactive material whose half-life is <m>25</m> days. Write an explicit function for the amount of thorium-<m>234</m> left after <m>t</m> days.  What percent of an original amount is left after <m>300</m> days?</p>
      </statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise>
      <statement>
        <p>The population of The Peoples Republic of China in <m>2015</m> was a little over <m>1.39</m> billion and growing at a rate of about <m>0.5\%</m> annually.
        <ol>
          <li>Write a recursive system to model the population</li>
          <li>Find an explicit function to model the population</li>
          <li>To the nearest year, how long will it take the population to double? Assume that the growth rate remains <m>0.5\%</m> per year.</li>
          <li>Use the doubling time you found in part (c) to write an transformation of the function <m>y=2^x</m> to represent China's population. (Use <m>x</m> to represent the number of years elapsed since <m>2015</m>.).</li>
          <li>Write a few sentences to compare and contrast the models you found in parts a, b, and d. </li>
        </ol>
        </p>
      </statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise>
      <statement>
        <p>When you are <m>40</m> years old your rich Uncle Harry leaves you <m>\$10,000</m> in his will when he dies.  His death makes you realize it is time to start saving for your own retirement. Your goal is to deposit enough in a retirement account when you are between the ages of <m>40</m> and <m>65</m> that you can "pay yourself" a comfortable amount each year when you are over <m>65</m>.
        <ol>
          <li>On your <m>40^{th}</m> birthday you invest the <m>\$10,000</m> in an account that pays <m>3.5\%</m> annual interest.  You also decide to make a yearly deposit in the account of <m>\$1,000</m>. What will your balance be when you turn <m>65</m>?  Give the amount in your account when you turn <m>65</m> and write the equations you use to arrive at your answer.</li>
          <li>Will you have enough money in your account when you are <m>65</m> to pay yourself <m>\$5,000</m> per year from age <m>65</m> to age <m>80</m>.  While you are withdrawing money, the balance in the account continues to earn <m>3.5\%</m> annual interest.  Give a yes or no answer and write the equations you use to support your answer.</li>
        </ol>
        </p>
      </statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise>
      <statement>
        <p>Thomas has two plans for saving to buy a car.  In Plan A, he will make an initial deposit of <m>\$50</m> and then he will deposit <m>\$33</m> each week in an account that earns <m>0.1\%</m> interest per week.  In Plan B, he will make an initial deposit of <m>\$50</m> and then each week he will put <m>\$30</m> in an account that earns <m>0.45\%</m> each week. Write recursive equations to show the amounts Thomas would have under each of the plans. Write down the account balances under each plan during weeks <m>1 - 3</m> and during weeks <m>50 - 52</m></p>
      </statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise>
      <statement>
        <p>In this section you have seen that the recursive system <m>P_0=a, P_n=(1+k) \cdot P_{n-1}, n = 1, 2, 3, ...</m> can be written as a closed form exponential function <m>P(n)=a \cdot (1+k)^n</m>. What recursive system can be written as a closed form linear function of the form <m>y(n)=a+kn</m>? </p>
      </statement>
    </exercise>

  </exercises>

</section>
