<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!-- This file is part of the book                      -->
<!--                                                    -->
<!--   Contemporary Pre-Calculus Through Applications   -->
<!--                                                    -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2018  Mathematics Department, NCSSM  -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.       -->
<section xml:id="chapter05-section04" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Solving Exponential and Logarithmic Equations</title>
    <introduction>
      <p>In the preceding chapter, a problem about aspirin dosage provided the function <m>a = 14.91e^{-0.18t}</m> and asked you to use a graph to determine the time at which the aspirin concentration is <m>5</m> mg per cc of blood. What happens when we attempt to solve the equation <m>5 = 14.91e^{-0.18t}</m> algebraically? Dividing both sides by <m>14.91</m> gives approximately <m>0.335 = e^{-0.18t}</m>. How do we isolate the variable <m>t</m>?  We can say that <m>t</m> is the number, which when multiplied by <m>-0.18</m> and used as the exponent of <m>e</m> produces <m>0.335</m>.  Our goal is to write this statement using mathematical symbols.</p>

      <p>
        To rewrite <m>0.335 = e^{-0.18t}</m> so that <m>t</m> is isolated, we can use logarithms. Due to their inverse relationship, logarithms allow us to rewrite an exponential equation so that the exponent is isolated, as defined earlier in this chapter. In the aspirin dosage problem we can rewrite <m>0.335 = e^{-0.18t}</m> as <m>\log_e \left( 0.335 \right) = -0.18t</m>.
      </p>
      <p>
        We can use thhe calculator to evaluate <m>\log_e \left( 0.335 \right) = \ln \left( 0.335 \right) \approx -1.09</m> and solve the resulting equation.
        <md>
          <mrow>-1.09 \amp \approx -0.18t</mrow>
          <mrow>t \amp \approx 6.1</mrow>
        </md>
        to determine that the aspirin level is <m>5</m> mg per cc of blood after approximately <m>6.1</m> hours.
      </p>
      <example>
        <statement>
          <p>Solve each equation for <m>x</m>:
            <ol>
              <li><m>\log_3 \left( 3 \right) = 5</m></li>
              <li><m>\log_x \left( 20 \right) = 3</m></li>
              <li><m>x = 7^{3\log_7 \left( 2 \right)}</m></li>
            </ol>
          </p>
        </statement>
        <solution>
          <p>
            <ol>
              <li><m>\log_3 \left( x \right) = 5</m> can be rewritten as <m>3^5 = x</m>, so <m>x = 243</m>.</li>
              <li><m>\log_x \left( 20 \right) = 3</m> can be rewritten as <m>x^3 = 20</m>, so <m>x = \sqrt[3]{20} \approx 2.7144</m></li>
              <li><m>x = 7^{3\log_7 \left( 2 \right)}</m> can be rewritten as <m>x = 7 ^{\log_7 \left( 2^3 \right)} = 7 ^ {\log_7 \left( 8 \right)}</m>, so <m>x = 8</m></li>
            </ol>
          </p>
        </solution>
      </example>
      <p>Solving equations that involve exponents or logarithms often requires techniques that involve composition as well as laws of exponents and logarithms.</p>

      <example>
        <statement>
          <p>
            The population of the world, as of November 1, 2016, was estimated by the U. S. Census Bureau to be approximately <m>7.348</m> billion and was growing at an annual rate of approximately <m>1.13\%</m>. If this rate were to remain constant, how long would it take for the population of the world to reach <m>10</m> billion?
          </p>
        </statement>
        <solution>
          <p>If we assume that the rate of growth is a constant percent (of the current population) then the function that models this growth is <m>P(t)=7.348 \left( 1.0113 \right)^t</m>, where <m>t</m> represents the number of years since November 1, 2016, and <m>P(t)</m> represents population in billions.  Since we need to determine the value of <m>t</m> for which <m>P(t) = 10</m>, we need to solve the equation <m>10 = 7.348 \left( 1.0113 \right)^t</m>. Applying the log of both sides of this equation yields the following:
          <md>
            <mrow>\log \left( 10 \right) \amp = \log \left( 7.348 (1.0113)^t \right)</mrow>
            <mrow>\log \left( 10 \right) \amp = \log \left( 7.348 \right) + t \log \left( 1.0113 \right)</mrow>
          </md>
          Solving for <m>t</m> gives us <m>t = \frac{\log \left( 10 \right) - \log \left( 7.358 \right)}{\log \left( 1.0113 \right)} \approx 27.4243</m>. Thus we can estimate that the population of the world will reach <m>10</m> billion in just a little less than <m>27</m> years and <m>6</m> months, sometime in April of 2044. Note that we could have first divided by <m>7.348</m>, then taken the log of both sides of the equation <m>\frac{10}{7.348} = \left( 1.0133 \right) ^t</m>, and solved for <m>t</m> to obtain the same solution.
          </p>
          <p>
            In the solution above we applied the common logarithm. We can obtain the same answer by taking the natural logarithm of both sides as follows:
            <md>
              <mrow>10 \amp = 7.348 \left( 1.0113 \right) ^t</mrow>
              <mrow>\frac{10}{7.348} \amp = \left( 1.0113 \right) ^t</mrow>
              <mrow>\ln \left( \frac{10}{7.348} \right) \amp = \ln \left( 1.0113^t \right)</mrow>
              <mrow>\ln \left( \frac{10}{7.348} \right) \amp = t \ln \left( 1.0113 \right)</mrow>
            </md>
            Solving for <m>t</m> gives us:
            <md>
              <mrow>t = \frac{\ln \left( \frac{10}{7.348} \right)}{\ln \left( 1.0113 \right)} \approx 27.4243</mrow>
            </md>
          </p>
        </solution>
      </example>

      <example>
        <statement>
          <p>
            If a group of people are all asked to memorize a list of nonsense words, the percent of those who remember all of the words after <m>t</m> hours can be approximated by the logarithmic function <m>f(t) = 1 - k\ln \left( t + 1 \right)</m>, where <m>k</m> is a constant that depends on several factors, such as the length of the list of words.  If after <m>5</m> hours only <m>20\%</m> of the members of a group can remember all of the words, determine the value of <m>k</m>. Using this value of <m>k</m>, determine what percent remember all of the words after <m>1</m> hour. At what time will no one in the group be able to remember all of the words?
          </p>
        </statement>
        <solution>
          <p>
            Note first that <m>f(0) = 1</m>, which tells us that initially <m>100\%</m> of the people in the group know all the words. To determine the value of <m>k</m> we need to solve the equation <m>0.20 = 1 - k \ln \left( t + 1 \right)</m> for <m>k</m> when <m>t = 5</m>.
            <md>
              <mrow>0.20 \amp = 1 - k \ln \left( 5 + 1 \right)</mrow>
              <mrow>-0.80 \amp = -k \ln \left( 6 \right)</mrow>
              <mrow>k \amp = \frac{0.80}{\ln(6)} \approx 0.446</mrow>
            </md>
            Using this value of <m>k</m> we know need to determine the value of <m>f(1)</m>.
            <md>
              <mrow>f(1) \amp = 1 - 0.446 \ln \left( 1 + 1 \right)</mrow>
              <mrow> \amp = 1 - 0.446 \ln \left( 2 \right)</mrow>
              <mrow> \amp \approx 0.691</mrow>
            </md>
            Since <m>f(1) \approx 0.691</m>, after one hour about <m>69\%</m> of the group still remembers all of the words. Finally, to determine how long it will take until no one in the group can remember all the words, we need to solve the following equation for <m>t</m>:
            <md>
              <mrow>0 \amp = 1 - 0.446 \ln \left( t + 1 \right)</mrow>
              <mrow>-1 \amp = -0.446 \ln \left( t + 1 \right)</mrow>
              <mrow>\frac{1}{0.446} \amp = \ln \left( t + 1 \right)</mrow>
            </md>
            At this point in the solution, we can exponentiate both sides of the equation, so that:
            <md>
              <mrow>e^{ \frac{1}{0.446}} \amp = e^{\ln \left( t + 1 \right)}</mrow>
              <mrow>e^{ \frac{1}{0.446}} \amp = t + 1</mrow>
              <mrow>t \amp = e^{ \frac{1}{0.446}} - 1</mrow>
            </md>
            Evaluating <m>t</m>, we find that <m>t \approx 8.4</m>. Thus, after about <m>8.4</m> hours, no one in the group can remember all of the words. For values of <m>t</m> larger than <m>8.4</m>, the function <m>f</m> would produce negative values for the percent, which would not make sense in this context.
          </p>
        </solution>
      </example>
    </introduction>

    <subsection>
      <title>Change of Base</title>
        <p>
          Mara was writing a report on the life of Marie Curie.  She found that in 1921, President Warren G. Harding presented Marie Curie with <m>1</m> gram of radium on behalf of the women of the United States.  Although not essential to her report, two of Mara's references gave a function to describe the decay of radium. One text gave the function describing the amount of radium left after <m>t</m> years to be <m>R_1(t) = 2^{-0.0006039t}</m> and the other as <m>R_2(t) = 1 \cdot e^{-0.0004186t}</m>.  Mara was curious about the two different functions given in her references. After thinking about the two functions for a while, Mara realized that they were the same function, only written in two different bases.
        </p>

        <p>
          We know that <m>3^4 = 9^2</m> and that <m>2^{-2} = \left( \frac{1}{16} \right)^{frac{1}{2}}</m>. Using a calculator, we can see that <m>5^2 \approx e^3.22</m> and that <m>2^{-0.0006039} \approx e^{-0.0004186}</m>. How do we change from one exponential base to another? When is it useful to do so? These questions are very important when we write exponential functions as models of real-world phenomena. Equivalent functions may look different because they are written with a different base.
        </p>

        <p>
          Let's investigate how we can express <m>f(x) = 2^x</m> as an exponential function with base <m>e</m>. We need to express <m>2</m> as a power of <m>e</m>, say <m>e^k</m>. So we must solve the equation <m>2 = e^k</m> to find <m>k</m>.  Both sides of this equation are positive, so we can use the technique of taking logarithms of both sides of the equation. Since the exponential component has a base of e, choosing a natural log will simplify the resulting work that follows:

          <md>
            <mrow>2 \amp = e^k</mrow>
            <mrow>\ln \left( 2 \right) \amp = \ln \left( e^k \right)</mrow>
            <mrow>\ln \left( 2 \right) \amp = k</mrow>
            <mrow>0.693 \amp \approx k</mrow>
          </md>

          So,
          <md>
            <mrow>2 = e^k = e^{\ln(2)} \approx e^{0.693}</mrow>
          </md>

          and we can write:
          <md>
            <mrow>f(x) = 2^x \approx \left( e^{0.693} \right)^x = e^{0.693x}</mrow>
          </md>

          This explains the difference in the two functions Mara found, Since
          <md>
            <mrow>R_1(t) = 2^{-0.0006039t} = \left( e^{\left( ln(2) \right)} \right)^{\left( -0.0006039 \right) t} = e^{\left( -0.0006039 \right) \left( ln(2) \right) t } = e^{-0.0004186t}</mrow>
          </md>

          Since exponential and logarithmic functions are inverses, you might suspect that we can also change the base of logarithmic functions.  Let's try to rewrite <m>g(x) = \log_2 \left( x \right)</m> with a natural logarithm. Let
          <md>
            <mrow>g(x) = y = \log_2 \left( x \right)</mrow>
          </md>

          and then rewrite this equation as
          <md>
            <mrow>2^y = x</mrow>
          </md>

          We now take the natural logarithm of both sides (which are positive):
          <md>
            <mrow>\ln \left( 2^y \right) \amp = \ln \left( x \right)</mrow>
            <mrow>y \ln \left( 2 \right) \amp = \ln \left( x \right)</mrow>
            <mrow>y \amp = \frac{\ln \left( x \right)}{\ln \left( 2 \right)} \approx 1.44 \ln \left( x \right)</mrow>
          </md>

          Therefore,
          <md>
            <mrow>g(x) = \log_2 \left( x \right) \approx 1.44 \ln \left( x \right)</mrow>
          </md>

        </p>

        <example>
          <statement>
            <p>
              Evaluate <m>\log_3 \left( 7 \right)</m>. Round your approximation to the thousandths place.
            </p>
          </statement>
          <solution>
            <p>
              Certain calculators and computers can compute logarithms of any base. However, many applications or computers are not be able to directly evaluate <m>\log_3 \left( 7 \right)</m>. We can use the techniques above to change the base and then evaluate using a base, such as <m>e</m> or <m>10</m>, that the computer can calculate.
            </p>

            <p>
              Let <m>y = \log_3 \left( 7 \right)</m>, and rewrite this equation in exponential form, <m>3^y = 7</m>.
            </p>

            <p>
              Since we now have an exponential equation, we can apply either the common log or the natural log of both sides of the equation as shown below.
            </p>

            <sidebyside>
              <p>
                <md>
                  <mrow>3^y \amp = 7</mrow>
                  <mrow>\log \left( 3^y \right) \amp \log \left( 7 \right)</mrow>
                  <mrow>y \log \left( 3 \right) \amp \log \left( 7 \right)</mrow>
                  <mrow>y \amp = \frac{ \log \left( 7 \right) }{\log \left( 3 \right)}</mrow>
                  <mrow>y \amp \approx 1.771</mrow>
                </md>
              </p>

              <p>
                <md>
                  <mrow>3^y \amp = 7</mrow>
                  <mrow>\ln \left( 3^y \right) \amp \ln \left( 7 \right)</mrow>
                  <mrow>y \ln \left( 3 \right) \amp \ln \left( 7 \right)</mrow>
                  <mrow>y \amp = \frac{ \ln \left( 7 \right) }{\ln \left( 3 \right)}</mrow>
                  <mrow>y \amp \approx 1.771</mrow>
                </md>
              </p>
            </sidebyside>
          </solution>
        </example>

        <p>
          The technique illustrated in the preceding example can be used to change the base of any logarithm. To find <m>\log_a \left( b \right)</m>, let <m>y = \log_a \left( b \right)</m>.
        </p>
        <p>
          Then,
          <md>
            <mrow>a^y \amp = b</mrow>
            <mrow>\log_c \left( a^y \right) \amp = \log_c \left( b \right)</mrow>
            <mrow>y \log_c \left( a \right) \amp = \log_c \left( b \right)</mrow>
            <mrow>y \amp = \frac{ \log_c \left( b \right)}{ \log_c \left( a \right)}</mrow>
          </md>
          So,
          <md>
            <mrow>log_a \left( b \right) = \frac{ \log_c \left( b \right) }{\log_c \left( a \right)}</mrow>
          </md>
        </p>

        <example xml:id="japan-growth-rate">
          <statement>
            <p>
              In recent years the population of Japan has been growing at an annual rate of about <m>0.3\%</m>. If we assume that this rate remains constant, how long will it take for the population to double?  How long will it take for the population to quadruple?
            </p>
          </statement>
          <solution>
            <p>
              When we solved a problem similar to this one earlier in the chapter, we did not have an analytical way to determine the doubling time. Logarithms provide such a way. Since the population is assumed to grow at a constant annual growth rate, each year the population is <m>1.003</m> times the previous year's population. If the current population of Japan is some number <m>N</m>, then it will be <m>2N</m> when the population doubles. So, we need to solve the equation <m>2N = N \left( 1.003 \right)^t</m>, where <m>t</m> is the number of years necessary for doubling. This yields
              <md>
                <mrow>2N \amp = N \left( 1.003 \right)^t</mrow>
                <mrow>2 \amp = \left( 1.003 \right)^t</mrow>
                <mrow>\ln \left( 2 \right) \amp = \ln \left( 1.003 \right)^t</mrow>
                <mrow>\ln \left( 2 \right) \amp = t \left( \ln \left( 1.003 \right) \right)</mrow>
                <mrow>t \amp = \frac{2}{\ln \left( 1.003 \right)}</mrow>
                <mrow>t \amp \approx 231.4</mrow>
              </md>
              From this solution, we see that the population in Japan will double in approximately <m>231.4</m> years, assuming a continuation of the current annual growth rate of <m>0.3\%</m>.  If this growth rate does not change, the population should quadruple in two doubling times, or approximately <m>462.8</m> years. This can be verified algebraically by solving the equation <m>4N = N \left( 1.003 \right)^t</m> for <m>t</m>.
            </p>
          </solution>
        </example>

        <example xml:id="arch-half-life">
          <statement>
            <p>
              Suppose an archaeologist finds a piece of human bone fragment that contains <m>43\%</m> of the amount of radioactive carbon-14 <fn>Carbon-14 is useful in the dating of relatively old artifacts and fossils because its half-life is relatively long. However, if we wanted to measure the age of objects that were millions of years old, the carbon-14 dating process would be useless, because virtually all of the carbon-14 present in the organism at death would have decayed away.  Scientists use isotopes of uranium and thorium to date very old objects. Similarly, carbon-14 dating is not useful in dating material from the last few decades, since the abundance of carbon-14 in the material is virtually indistinguishable from the amount of carbon-14 in living matter.  Tritium, with a half-life of 12.1 years, is often used for dating more recent matter such as wines.</fn> normally found in the bone of a living person.  She knows that the half-life of carbon-14 is <m>5,730</m> years. How old is the bone?
            </p>
          </statement>
          <solution>
            <p>
              First, since less than half the carbon-14 remains, we know that the bone is more than <m>5,730</m> years old. To find a more precise answer, we could first determine the general equation <m>P(t) = P_0 e^{kt}</m> and find the value of <m>k</m>. Since the half-life of carbon-14 is <m>5,730</m> years, we know that the initial value of <m>P_0</m> will have decayed to <m>0.5P_0</m> when <m>t = 5,730</m>. Therefore, we can write the equation <m>0.5P_0 = P_0 e^{5730k}</m>, and solve for <m>k</m> as follows:
              <md>
                <mrow>0.5P_0 \amp = P_0 e^{5730k}</mrow>
                <mrow>0.5 \amp = e^{5730k}</mrow>
                <mrow>\ln \left( 0.5 \right) \amp = 5730k</mrow>
                <mrow> k \amp = \frac{ \ln \left( 0.5 \right) }{5730}</mrow>
                <mrow> k \amp \approx -0.000121</mrow>
              </md>
              We can now write the equation <m>P(t) = P_0 e^{-0.000121t}</m>. We want to determine the value of <m>t</m> when <m>P(t) = 0.43P_0</m>, so we need to solve the following equation

              <md>
                <mrow>0.43P_0 \amp = P_0 e^{-0.000121t}</mrow>
                <mrow>0.43 \amp = e^{-0.000121t}</mrow>
                <mrow>\ln \left( 0.43 \right) \amp = -0.000121t</mrow>
                <mrow>t \amp = \frac{\ln \left( 0.43 \right)}{-0.000121}</mrow>
                <mrow>t \amp \approx 6975 \text{years}</mrow>
              </md>

              We conclude, therefore, that the bone is approximately <m>6,975</m> years old.
            </p>
          </solution>
        </example>

    </subsection>

    <exercises>
      <title>Class Practice</title>
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
            Rework <xref ref="japan-growth-rate" text="type-local" /> by first writing a function for the population of Japan in the form <m>P(t) = ae^{kt}</m> and then solving for the doubling time.
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>

      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
            Verify from your work in the preceding exercise that <m>\frac{\ln(2)}{k}</m> is a general expression for the doubling time when the population function is written in the form <m>P(t) = ae^{kt}</m>.
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>

      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
            Let <m>g</m> represent the annual growth rate of a population expressed in decimal form.  Explain why the expression <m>\frac{ln(2)}{g}</m> provides a good approximation of doubling time whenever <m>g</m> is small (less than <m>20\%</m>).
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>

      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
            Write a function for the population of Japan using base <m>2</m>. Explain why this base is useful in solving doubling-time problems.
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
            Solve <xref ref="arch-half-life" text="type-local" /> using base <m>\frac{1}{2}</m>. Explain why this is a simpler base for half-life problems
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>
    </exercises>

    <exercises>
      <!-- Exercise 1 -->
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
            Rewrite <m>g(x) = \left( \frac{1}{2} \right)^x</m> as an exponential function with base 10.
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>

      <!-- Exercise 2 -->
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
            Dot and Dan plan to invest <m>\$5,000</m> in an account that pays <m>9\%</m> annual interest compounded monthly. Write three closed form expressions for the future value of the account after <m>N</m> years. Use <m>\left( 1 + \frac{0.09}{12} \right)</m>, <m>2</m>, and <m>e</m> as bases.
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>

      <!-- Exercise 3 -->
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
            A house purchased four years ago for <m>\$40,000</m> was sold for <m>\$60,000</m>. If the value of the house continues to increase exponentially at the same rate, how much will it be worth next year?
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>

      <!-- Exercise 4 -->
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
            Find the continuously compounded interest rate that is equivalent to <m>10\%</m> compounded quarterly.
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>

      <!-- Exercise 5 -->
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
            <ol>
              <li>Show that <m>\frac{\ln \left( \frac{1}{2} \right)}{k}</m> is a general expression for half-life when the decay function is written as <m>P(t) = P_0 e^{kt}</m>.</li>
              <li>Find an expression for half-life if the decay function is written as <m>P(t) = P_0 2^{kt}</m>.</li>
            </ol>
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>

      <!-- Exercise 6 -->
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
            When a certain drug enters the blood stream, it is absorbed gradually by body tissue, and its concentration decreases exponentially with a half-life of <m>3</m> days. If the initial concentration of the drug in the blood stream is <m>A</m>, what will the concentration be <m>30</m> days later? Assume that no additional doses are taken.
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>

      <!-- Exercise 7 -->
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
            Given a population of <m>10</m> million and an annual growth rate of <m>3\%</m>, how long will it take this population to double?  What is the size of the population in triple the doubling time?
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>

      <!-- Exercise 8 -->
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
            A population of bacteria is growing exponentially. A researcher determines the population of the bacteria to be <m>2,000</m> at <m>2\:00</m> and to be <m>4,000</m> at <m>2\:10</m>. What is the doubling time of the population?  What is the estimated population at <m>2\:05</m>?
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>

      <!-- Exercise 9 -->
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
            Carbon-11 decays into boron at the rate of roughly <m>3.5\%</m> per minute. What is the half-life of carbon-11?
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>

      <!-- Exercise 10 -->
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>What exponential function of the form <m>y = ae^{bx}</m> goes through the following points?
            <ol>
              <li><m>\left( 0, 3 \right)</m> and <m>\left( 5, 80 \right)</m></li>
              <li><m>\left( 3, 10 \right)</m> and <m>\left( 6, 50 \right)</m></li>
            </ol>
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>

      <!-- Exercise 11 -->
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
            A local bank advertises that if you deposit at least <m>\$5,000</m> in an investment account your money will double in <m>8</m> years. Assuming that interest is compounded monthly, find the interest rate on the account.
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>

      <!-- Exercise 12 -->
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
            Cesium-137, one of the dangerous radionucleides produced in the fallout of the Chernobyl disaster, has a half-life of <m>30.3</m> years. How much time must pass before the radiation emitted by the radioactive cesium is reduced to <m>10\%</m> of the amount produced in the Chernobyl explosion?
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>

      <!-- Exercise 13 -->
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
            When money is deposited in a savings account, the balance increases exponentially. The time required for the balance to double is constant, regardless of the amount deposited. Let <m>A</m> represent the amount deposited into the account, <m>N</m> represent the number of years the money is left in the account, <m>I</m> represent the annual interest rate as a decimal, and <m>k</m> represent the number of compounding periods per year.
            <ol>
              <li>To determine a general formula for doubling time, solve the equation <m>2A = A \left( 1 + \frac{I}{k} \right)^{kN}</m> for <m>N</m> in terms of <m>I</m> and <m>k</m>.</li>
              <li>Use this formula to verify several doubling times in <xref ref="freq-of-compounding" text="type-local" /></li>
              <li>
                <p>
                  Describe how doubling time changes as interest rate and frequency of compounding change.
                  <figure xml:id="freq-of-compounding">
                    <caption>Doubling Time in Years</caption>
                    <tabular top="major" halign="center">
                      <row bottom="medium">
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell>Yearly (<m>k = 1</m>)</cell>
                        <cell>Quarterly (<m>k = 4</m>)</cell>
                        <cell>Daily (<m>k = 365</m>)</cell>
                        <cell>Continuous (<m>k \rightarrow \infty</m>)</cell>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <cell halign="left"><m>0.05</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>14.21</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>13.95</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>13.86</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>13.86</m></cell>
                      </row>

                      <row>
                        <cell halign="left"><m>0.08</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>9.01</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>8.75</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>8.67</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>8.66</m></cell>
                      </row>

                      <row>
                        <cell halign="left"><m>0.10</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>7.27</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>7.02</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>6.93</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>6.93</m></cell>
                      </row>

                      <row>
                        <cell halign="left"><m>0.12</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>6.12</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>5.86</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>5.78</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>5.78</m></cell>
                      </row>

                      <row bottom="major">
                        <cell halign="left"><m>0.15</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>4.96</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>4.71</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>4.62</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>4.62</m></cell>
                      </row>
                    </tabular>
                  </figure>
                </p>
              </li>
            </ol>
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>

      <!-- Exercise 14 -->
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
            Bankers often approximate doubling time with the Rules of <m>69</m>, <m>70</m>, and <m>72</m>.  In the previous exercise you should have found that exact doubling time is given by:
            <md>
              <mrow>N = \frac{ \ln \left( 2 \right)}{ \ln \left( 1 + \frac{I}{k} \right)^k}</mrow>
            </md>
            where <m>I</m> is the stated annual percentage rate and <m>k</m> the number of compounding periods per year.
          </p>
          <p>
            In the case of continuous compounding, where <m>k \rightarrow \infty</m> and <m>\left( 1 + \frac{I}{k} \right)^k \rightarrow e^t</m>,
            <md>
              <mrow>N = \frac{ \ln \left( 2 \right)}{\ln \left( e^t \right)} = \frac{ \ln \left( 2 \right)}{I} \approx \frac{0.6931472}{I} \approx \frac{69}{100I}</mrow>
            </md>
            Thus, bankers can approximate doubling time with <m>N \approx \frac{69}{100I}</m>, which is commonly referred to as the Rule of <m>69</m>.
            <ol>
              <li>Use the Rule of <m>69</m> to estimate the doubling time for money invested at a rate of <m>8\%</m> compounded continuously.</li>
              <li>Verify several estimates for doubling time in <xref ref="freq-of-compounding" text="type-local" />.</li>
              <li>
                <p>
                  Sometime the 69 in the numerator is replaced with 70 or 72. Compare the entries in <xref ref="freq-of-compounding" text="type-local" /> and <xref ref="rules-of-69-70-72" text="type-local" /> to determine which approximation is more appropriate for yearly compounding.  Which is more appropriate for quarterly compounding?  For daily compounding?

                  <figure xml:id="rules-of-69-70-72">
                    <caption>Doubling Time Approximations in Years</caption>
                    <tabular top="major" halign="center">
                      <row bottom="medium">
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell><m>\frac{69}{100I}</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>\frac{70}{100I}</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>\frac{72}{100I}</m></cell>
                      </row>

                      <row>
                        <cell halign="left"><m>0.05</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>13.80</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>14.00</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>14.40</m></cell>
                      </row>

                      <row>
                        <cell halign="left"><m>0.08</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>8.63</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>8.75</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>9.00</m></cell>
                      </row>

                      <row>
                        <cell halign="left"><m>0.10</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>6.90</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>7.00</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>7.20</m></cell>
                      </row>

                      <row>
                        <cell halign="left"><m>0.12</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>5.75</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>5.83</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>6.00</m></cell>
                      </row>

                      <row bottom="major">
                        <cell halign="left"><m>0.15</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>4.60</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>4.67</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>4.80</m></cell>
                      </row>
                    </tabular>
                  </figure>
                </p>
              </li>
            </ol>
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>

      <!-- Exercise 15 -->
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
            Change <m>\log_b \left( a \right)</m> to an expression involving logarithms with base <m>c</m>.
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>

      <!-- Exercise 16 -->
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
            Rewrite <m>\log \left( x \right)</m> using the natural logarithm.
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>

      <!-- Exercise 17 -->
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
            Show that <m>\left( \log_a \left( b \right) \right) \left( \log_b \left( a \right) \right) = 1</m> for all <m>a \gt 0, b \gt 0</m>.
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>

      <!-- Exercise 18 -->
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
            Solve the following equations for <m>x</m>. Give exact values whenever possible.
            <ol>
              <li><m>\log_x \left( 27 \right) = -3</m></li>
              <li><m>\log_{64} \left( x \right) = \frac{2}{3}</m></li>
              <li><m>x = 5^{2 \log_5 \left( 5 \right)}</m></li>
              <li><m>\log_6 \left( x^2 \right) = -2</m></li>
              <li><m>\log_2 \left( x^2 + 5x + 10 \right) = 4</m></li>
              <li><m>\log_{\frac{1}{x}} \left( 9 \right) = 2</m></li>
            </ol>
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>

      <!-- Exercise 19 -->
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
            Solve the following equations for <m>x</m>. Give exact values whenever possible.
            <ol>
              <li><m>5^x = 3</m></li>
              <li><m>5^{x-1} = e^x</m></li>
              <li><m>3^{x+1} = 9^x \cdot 27^{x+1}</m></li>
              <li><m>\log_x \left( 12 \right) = 3</m></li>
              <li><m>\ln \left( \ln \left( x + 6 \right) \right) = 0</m></li>
              <li><m>10^{2x+1} = 4^{x-1}</m></li>
              <li><m>e^{x^2} = 10</m></li>
              <li><m>5^{3x-2} = 3^{x+1}</m></li>
              <li><m>\log_2 \left( x + 4 \right) + \log_2 \left( x + 2 \right) = \log_2 \left( 3 \right)</m> (Be careful with the domain!)</li>
              <li><m>\log \left( x^4 \right) = \left( \log \left( x \right) \right)^3</m></li>
              <li><m>5^{x^2 - x} = 7</m></li>
              <li><m>5^{2x} - 7 \left( 5^x \right) + 12 = 0</m></li>
            </ol>
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>

      <!-- Exercise 20 -->
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
            Solve each equation for the indicated variable:
            <ol>
              <li>Solve for <m>t: e^{rt} = 2</m></li>
              <li>Solve for <m>k: T = Ae^{-bk} + C</m></li>
              <li>Solve for <m>t: S = A \ln \left( Bt + C \right)</m></li>
              <li>Solve for <m>c: y = \frac{A}{1 + Be^{-Acx}}</m></li>
              <li>Solve for <m>y: \ln \left( y - 10 \right) = \ln \left( a \right) + bx</m></li>
              <li>Solve for <m>y: \ln \left( y \right) = \ln \left( a \right) + b \ln \left( x \right)</m></li>
            </ol>
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>

      <!-- Exercise 21 -->
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
            Find the inverse of each of the following functions and identify the domain of each:
            <ol>
              <li><m>f(x) = 2^{x+1} - 3</m></li>
              <li><m>f(x) = 3 \ln \left( 2x \right)</m></li>
              <li><m>f(x) = e^{2x} + 1</m></li>
              <li><m>f(x) = \frac{ \ln \left( x + 5 \right) }{2}</m></li>
            </ol>
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>

    </exercises>
</section>
