<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!-- This file is part of the book                      -->
<!--                                                    -->
<!--   Contemporary Pre-Calculus Through Applications   -->
<!--                                                    -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2017  Mathematics Department, NCSSM  -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.       -->

<section xml:id="chapter01-section01" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Some Thoughts about Models and Mathematics</title>
    <p>When children think about models, they are generally considering some kind of a toy, perhaps an airplane or a dinosaur. When scientists and mathematicians think about models, they are generally considering a model as a tool, even though they may be thinking about the same airplane or dinosaur. Scientists and mathematicians use models to help them study and understand the physical world. People in all walks of life use models to help them solve problems; problems in this course will involve models used by bankers, anthropologists, geologists, and many, many others.</p>

    <p>So just what is a model? Models are simplified representations of phenomena. To be useful, a model must share important characteristics with the phenomenon it represents, and it must also be simpler than what it represents. A model usually differs significantly from what it represents, but these differences are offset by the advantage that comes from simplifying the phenomenon. A good example is a road map, which models the streets and highways in a particular area. Clearly, a map has a lot in common with the actual streets and highways it shows how roads are oriented and where they intersect. A road map simplifies the situation; it ignores stoplights, hills, and back alleys and instead focuses on major thoroughfares. Such a map is very useful for traveling from one city to another, but is not much good for finding the quickest route to the shopping mall or the best street for skateboarding. Road maps, and most other models, are useful precisely because they ignore some information and thereby allow you to see other information more clearly.</p>

    <p>Another fairly common model is an EKG, which models the electrical activity of the heart. The EKG is an excellent model when used to determine the heart rate or to find which regions of the heart may be damaged after a heart attack. It is not a useful model for determining the volume of blood flowing through the heart. Different models emphasize different aspects of a phenomenon; the choice of which model to use depends on which aspect is under investigation.</p>

    <p>The ability to predict is the ultimate test for a model. A good model allows us to make accurate predictions about what will occur under certain conditions. If what actually occurs is very different from our prediction, then the model is of little use. Scientists and mathematicians often need to update or revise models as more is learned about the phenomenon under study. Sometimes a model needs to be completely discarded and replaced with a new one. For example, before Columbus sailed to the Americas, many people believed the world was flat, but that model was quickly abandoned in light of new information.</p>

    <p>Even though Isaac Newton’s models for the actions of a gravitational field have been replaced by Einstein’s relativistic model, we still use Newtonian physics in many situations because it is easier and because it gives reasonably accurate results. The aspects of Einstein's mechanics that are ignored are largely irrelevant in most everyday applications, so the Newtonian model is still a good one.</p>

    <p>As we move through the course, we will encounter phenomena that we want to know more about. Our task will be to find a mathematical expression or a graph that mimics the phenomenon we are interested in. This model must accurately represent the aspects of the phenomenon that we care about, but it may be very different from the phenomenon in other ways. To be able to find a model to represent a problem, we need to have a large toolkit of mathematical information and techniques at our disposal. The fundamental concepts of Algebra and Geometry are all a part of our toolkit. We will also use the calculator and computer as tools to construct and analyze models for the phenomena we study. Probably the most important tools necessary for making models are an inquisitive mind and a determined spirit.</p>

    <p>Often we will not stop after we have developed one model but will form two or three to get a better view of the subject. For example, suppose a rock is thrown vertically into the air. How can its height be modeled? We can use a graph as a model for this phenomenon (see <xref ref="height-of-a-rock-over-time" text="type-local" />).</p>

      <figure xml:id="height-of-a-rock-over-time">
        <caption>Height of a rock over time</caption>

        <image>
          <latex-image>
            <![CDATA[
            \begin{tikzpicture}
              \begin{axis}[
                xlabel = Time (in seconds),
                ylabel = Height (in meters),
                ylabel near ticks,
                xlabel near ticks,
                xmin = 0,
                xmax = 6,
                ymin = 0,
                ymax = 35,
                ]

                \addplot [thick, blue, mark=none, domain=0:5,samples=200] {-1*5*x^2 + 25*x};

              \end{axis}
            \end{tikzpicture}]]>
          </latex-image>
        </image>
      </figure>

    <p>We can also describe the height by an equation. If the height above the ground is represented by <m>h</m> and the time is represented by <m>t</m>, then a simple model for the height as a function of time is <m>h = -4.9t^2 + 25.1t + 1</m>.</p>

    <p>Notice that these models do not give complete information about the problem. We cannot tell from the models what type of rock was thrown, who threw it, or why. These aspects of the problem are not relevant, since all we really care about is height and time. Both models give this information. The strength of any model is in what it emphasizes and what it ignores.</p>

</section>
